tempe.gov 2006-09-23

# Privacy Policy - City of Tempe

Tempe in Touch  
City of Tempe web site  
Privacy policy  
April 30, 2001

**Will the City of Tempe disclose the information it collects to outside parties?**  
The City of Tempe does not sell, trade, or rent your personal information to others. The City of Tempe may provide aggregate statistics about our customers, traffic patterns, and related site information to other government agencies, but these statistics will include no personal identifying information. The City of Tempe may release account information when we believe, in good faith, that such release is reasonably necessary to (i) comply with law, (ii) enforce or apply the terms of any of our user agreements or (iii) protect the rights, property or safety of the City of Tempe, our users, or others.

****

**Your consent**  
By using the Tempe in Touch web site, you consent to the collection and use of this information by the City of Tempe. If we decide to change our privacy policy, we will post those changes on this page so that you always have the opportunity to be aware of what information we collect, how we use it, and under what circumstances we disclose it.

**Forms**  
All forms on our site should be set to automatically run as secured forms.  That means you should see the same security lock indication on your browser as you would if you were in a shopping cart or banking site.  In the event that you find a form that is not secure please report it to [webmaster@tempe.gov](mailto:webmaster@tempe.gov) with the web address of the form.  To make any page on the Tempe.gov web site secure you may add an 's' to the web address right after the http in the address line.  For example, this page would be [ https://www.tempe.gov/privacy.htm](https://www.tempe.gov/privacy.htm) (updated 8/2005)

****

**Specifically Cookies  
**The technical term for tracking a visitor on a web site is ‘Cookies’. Some maintain that cookies, in any form, are bad. We agree that they ‘can’ be bad, however, there are important technical reasons to use cookies in limited situations, and the Tempe web site does use cookies in a limited manner as stated below.

It is important to understand what a cookie is and how it works in order to understand how and why we use it. When someone visits a web site, they are requesting a page of information, and that information is sent to their browser, and their connection to the web site is then broken within seconds. The web site has no record of who just received the page. For most visits this is fine. This is a transaction that does not require cookies and is the most common.

A cookie is a very small file that is stored on the visiting users computer by their browser when requested by the web server. For example, if you are using web pages that are more sophisticated than standard pages, the web server might need a way to determine one user from another. Remember, you are only connected for a few seconds and hundreds of others might be served before you get your next page from the server.

Lets take an example of a multi-page form on the web. As you fill in one form and move on to the next, the server will need a way to remember where you are in the form process, and what previous forms you have filled in so that it can keep them together. When you submit page one there is a cookie stored on your computer with a temporary id tag and a marker saying what web server gave it to you. This cookie will not have any personal information and takes less space on your hard drive than one line in this document. Now, as you bring up page two, the server asks your browser if you have a cookie, and that id tag information is sent to the server, thus reminding it who you are – as opposed to the other 100 people filling out the same form at the same time. This process basically keeps you in a personal exchange with the server.

If you have ever purchased something over the web the vendor uses cookies to keep track of you and from that they can track what you have already selected in your shopping cart.

Cookies can also be used for more devious things. Tracking how many times 'you' specifically come to a web site for example. Tracking what pages 'you' visit while you are at that site. These are tracking 'your' behavior, and this is considered bad.

The City will not use cookies, or any other technology, to track individuals on our web site. The only exception, as stated in the example above, would be to keep transactions open between the server and user during a session with an application. Those sessions usually expire 20 minutes after the last web page access, and in many cases, it’s never actually stored as a cookie file and expires as soon as the browser is closed.

****

**Email  
**Email as well as certain other documents in the City may be considered public record. Email sent to the mayor and any city council members are automatically forwarded to the media by their request.

****

**Cameras  
**Live cameras are used on the web site as a form of public relations. Although there are no laws pertaining to video and privacy (only audio or video with audio) we will continue to respect the privacy of our citizens. The cameras used on the web site will remain distant and unfocused enough that individual identification will be very unlikely. Sound will never be captured or broadcast. The cameras are for showing visitors the weather and general activity in the area. The only time the cameras may be used for surveillance will be during a large crowd event on Mill Avenue such as the Block Party, July 4th, or the Arts Festivals as examples.

****

**Tell us what you think**  
The City of Tempe welcomes your questions and comments about the privacy policy. Please send e-mail to webmaster@tempe.gov.
